<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://extentoftheworld.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://extentoftheworld.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-18T14:20:09-05:00</updated><id>http://extentoftheworld.net/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Review: A Desolation Called Peace by Arkady Martine</title><link href="http://extentoftheworld.net/reviews/2023/12/18/martine-desolation-called-peace.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review: A Desolation Called Peace by Arkady Martine" /><published>2023-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://extentoftheworld.net/reviews/2023/12/18/martine-desolation-called-peace</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://extentoftheworld.net/reviews/2023/12/18/martine-desolation-called-peace.html"><![CDATA[<p>The sequel to <em>A Memory Called Empire</em> sees Martine struggle to center a well-worn science fiction trope without significant new ideas. While <em>A Desolation Called Peace</em> is a touching romance and keeps some of the same political and character-driven charm of the first novel, the discovery story is lacking. Conditionally recommended.</p>

<h2 id="concept">Concept</h2>

<p>After diverting the Empire’s attention from Lsel Station by calling attention to a new alien threat from beyond the Anhemnemat Gate, the new Emperor Nineteen Adze sends new <em>yaotlek</em> Nine Hibiscus to confront the menace. Nine Hibiscus, struggling with her loyal friend and advisor Twenty Cicada to keep her subordinates in line and her fleet intact, calls for an <em>askreta</em> from the Information Ministry to assist her in her campaigns. Three Seagrass decides to send herself, picking up Ambassador Mahit Dzmare from Lsel Station as well in order to enlist her help in communicating with the aliens.</p>

<p>Mahit Dzmare’s return from Teixcalaan has not been good for her. Realizing that she and Yskandr essentially sold Lsel Station’s secret technology, Heritage Councilor Akhel Amnardbat is determined to see her gone and her imago discarded, and none of the other councilors seem interested in protecting her. She therefore takes Three Seagrass up on the offer and returns to serve the Empire.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, on Teixcalaan itself, Six Direction’s son and heir to Nineteen Adze, Eight Antidote, is learning more and more not only about warfare and administration but about the war unfolding beyond the Anhemnemat Gate. He’s got questions, and the ministers’ answers only seem to give him more. But what can some kid under the thumb of the Empire do, anyway?</p>

<h2 id="positives">Positives</h2>

<p>The relationship between Three Seagrass and Mahit Dzmare is oddly compelling. It’s very rare that I feel about a romance in a science fiction story anything other than “ugh, when will this be done so that we can get back to the interesting stuff?” Despite that, Martine manages to write something that has me consistently invested and desperately pleading for the two to reconcile, solve their problems, and end up together.</p>

<p>Eight Antidote ends up being a pivotal character in the story, which I like. Science fiction doesn’t completely lack children solving problems where adults were blind, but his plotting manages to simultaneously be clever, critical, and still childish.</p>

<p>The eventual way that Mahit escapes her persecution on Lsel is interesting — actually, overall, I’d say that her relationship with Lsel Station and Three Seagrass and the way love, loyalty, and nationality are intertwined with each is the real gold in this story. My problems with this book pretty much all stem from the fact that other things distracted me from what could have also just been a neat if rather mysterious short story about Mahit and Three Seagrass on Nine Hibiscus’s flagship investigating a vague and never-really-specified situation, where the story remains just about the spotlight characters and the way that nation, culture, and empire influence their motivations and relationships.</p>

<h2 id="negatives">Negatives</h2>

<p>There is no mystery in this story! The original had a deep web of plots that the reader needed to wade through with Mahit and Yskandr, trying to figure out the motivations and histories of all the other characters just as they did. <em>A Desolation Called Peace</em>, on the other hand, spoils itself: the very first thing in the book you read is from the perspective of the aliens, clearly demonstrating that are a hive mind — something that the book then acts, for the entire rest of its first half, as though it is some kind of clever secret to be figured out! The “Shard trick” that Nine Hibiscus and her subordinates are so cagey and mysterious about is similarly obvious, <em>especially</em> once the hive mind theme has already been so bluntly established. As a result, I was very frustrated reading a lot of the first contact bits, because it really just felt like I had nothing to do but wait for the charcters to realize the most obvious facts of their situation. The story might work a little better as written for readers not as familiar with the hive mind as a science fiction concept, but as it is, Martine seems to have commited the critical error of simulatenously revealing something and writing a story that depended on it not having been revealed.</p>

<p>Message-wise, “don’t genocide your enemies” is never going to go over too poorly with me. Theme-wise, though, I’m not so sure about this book. It takes a core similarity between Teixcalaanli and Stationer culture and decides to throw it aside in favor of an exploration of collective consciousness that really feels more like “Martine thought this seemed interesting” than “Martine has something interesting to say.” Like, what do I take away from the novel <em>about</em> collective consciousness? I’m not sure it really adds anything to the conversation.</p>

<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>

<p>This was a bit of a mixed bag: there were many points at which I was keenly invested in everything that was happening, but there were also many sections that I found purely frustrating to get through. Therefore, I would recommend this book only to fans of <em>A Memory Called Empire</em> who are desperately waiting to see what happens next in the world of Teixcalaan and Lsel Station. Read it for more of Martine’s insight into culture, but if you’re interested in the advertized first contact story, then I’d say to look elsewhere.</p>

<p>Again, thanks for reading this. If you think I’ve been unfair, don’t hesitate to reach out and let me know your own thoughts — I’d love to hear them. Have a good day!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The sequel to A Memory Called Empire sees Martine struggle to center a well-worn science fiction trope without significant new ideas. While A Desolation Called Peace is a touching romance and keeps some of the same political and character-driven charm of the first novel, the discovery story is lacking. Conditionally recommended.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review: A Memory Called Empire by Arkady Martine</title><link href="http://extentoftheworld.net/reviews/2023/12/17/martine-memory-called-empire.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review: A Memory Called Empire by Arkady Martine" /><published>2023-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://extentoftheworld.net/reviews/2023/12/17/martine-memory-called-empire</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://extentoftheworld.net/reviews/2023/12/17/martine-memory-called-empire.html"><![CDATA[<p>Arkady Martine’s breakout novel is a modern exploration of the cultural significance of empire. Full of political intrigue, enticing flavor, compelling characters, and well-developed relationships, this book is excellent despite minor issues mostly related to language. Highly recommended.</p>

<h2 id="concept">Concept</h2>

<p>Mahit Dzmare of Lsel Station has always been obsesssed with Teixcalaanli culture. She had read all about Teixcalaan, studied its language and customs, taken classes, and even — once, as an exercise — come up with a Teixcalaanli name. Naturally, then, when Lsel needs a new Ambassador to Teixcalaan, Mahit is the natural choice.</p>

<p>The main complications from her job all stem, more or less, from a technology omnipresent in and central to Stationer society: the imago machine. Stationers have snapshots taken from their lives and stored in imago machines, which their successors have surgically installed to gain their lives’ skills, experiences, and memories. This is kept strictly as a state secret from the Empire, but has been a key part of Stationer social structure for as long as its people can remember. The imago’s personality is also preserved, and for the period between the initial surgery and full integration, acts as a distinct voice-in-the-head type of presence for the host.</p>

<p>Mahit arrives in Teixcalaan to find her predecessor, Yskandr Aghavn, dead, and a shady investigation into why already underway. Her main ambassadorial duty — preventing Teixcalaan from invading Stationer space — more difficult than expected. Cultural shock hits quickly, even for a Teixcaboo like Mahit. And every time she tries to solve a problem, all she finds is more schemes and plots…</p>

<h2 id="positives">Positives</h2>

<p>I loved the intrigue, scheming, politics, and even poetry. Martine does a very good job of making it feel like Mahit really has walked right into an already-twisted web full of characters in conflict, and it gives the plot the perfect balance between crazy plot twists and “oh, so <em>that’s</em> what’s going on!” that made me feel rather smart at times as I was reading it.</p>

<p>The pacing was excellent: no chapters felt like drags, but it was also very rare that I wished any scene had been made much longer. The story starts slow, then accelerates, building more and more tension until all hell breaks loose — just what’s expected of the genre. By the end, I couldn’t stop reading the book. Well, actually, the whole thing was so gripping that I went through it all in one plane ride to Detroit.</p>

<p>I’d like to call special attention to the names Martine uses for Teixcalaanli characters. Each Teixcalaanlitzim has a name composed of a cardinal number and a thing, almost always a type of plant, something else from nature, or a cool science fiction word; examples include “Three Seagrass”, “One Lightning”, and “Nineteen Adze”. Wait, an adze? Yes, the theming is fairly loose, but I think having just a <em>general</em> trend towards plants and nature gives a lot to establish a poetic theme for Teixcalaanli society while also giving room for individual Teixcalaanlitzim to have names that stand out. Some readers of the book seem to struggle with keeping these names straight, which I can imagine, but I never had any problem with this myself… I guess that’s something that should be kept in mind, though.</p>

<p>It’s also interesting to me the way that Martine has set up Teixcalaan and Lsel Station as seeming very different and being constantly at odds — culturally, anyway — while really having very similar core values. Stationers may do through technology what Teixcalaanlitzim do through literature, but in the end, both societies are built around constantly emulating and even reliving the past. I’ll avoid going into some kind of deep analysis of the novel, but I do feel that <em>A Memory Called Empire</em> is symbolically rich enough to appeal to that kind of reader as well.</p>

<h2 id="negatives">Negatives</h2>

<p>The linguistics of Teixcalaanli are a bit strange. First off, the story stresses — numerous times, actually — that Teixcalaanlitzim have only one word for “the world” (all that exists), “the Empire” (of Teixcalaan), “the Planet” (of Teixcalaan), and “the City” (because the Planet Teixcalaan is, of course, an ecumenopolis). I just don’t really know how to feel about this. Having only one word for the Planet and the City makes sense, because they are basically the same thing. Having only one word for the Empire and the Planet is a little less natural, but it still feels to me both realistic and cool: after all, it’s how we talk about Rome. But talking about all things that exist as being the same thing as the Empire — to the extent that things outside the Empire are “outside of the world” — makes zero sense. Like, the military of Teixcalaan fights on the border and even conquers other planets. They have ambassadors. I understand that they have that imperialist mindset of “Lsel is only independent because we let them be, but we would be totally in the right to take them over,” but like, they are capable of recognizing and contrasting against the Empire things that lie outside of its administrative or military reach. Does the average Teixcalaanlitzim simply not acknowledge that alien threats exist? If so, that’s crazy. Otherwise, there must be some other word — besides “Teixcalaan”, I mean — that actually refers to things that exist but aren’t in the Empire. Right?</p>

<p>The other thing is that I don’t really know how I’m supposed to pronounce Teixcalaanli words because the pronunciation guide is clearly messed up (in both this book and its sequel, <em>A Desolation Called Peace</em>). Here are just three examples of the inconsistencies I notice:</p>

<ul>
  <li>&lt;aa&gt; is supposed to extend the length of the sound represented by &lt;a&gt; without changing its quality, and yet the IPA given has two different vowel qualities and the same lengths for each.</li>
  <li>&lt;l&gt;, according to the given IPA, apparently represents a voiced velar fricative (in most environments). You know, as in the words “bell” and “ball”. The only problem is that that’s not a voiced velar fricative, it’s a velarized alveolar lateral approximant, the IPA transcription of which shares a symbol (kinda) but is absolutely not the same.</li>
  <li>The IPA given for &lt;r&gt; conflicts with the American English examples because the rhotic in American English is definitely not an alveolar flap.</li>
</ul>

<p>To be clear, I’m not criticizing the book for being unrealistic. I just wish Martine had managed to describe Teixcalaanli phonetics in a more consistent way so that I were more confident in how words like “Teixclaanli” are actually supposed to be pronounced! Is this a nitpicky complaint? Yeah… but…</p>

<p>Maybe the fact that these are the big issues I can come up with means that the book is actually really good?</p>

<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>

<p>Yeah, those are the harshest negatives I could really think of. Everything else really was just little personal-taste stuff that (at least for now) I’m going to try to avoid on this blog. The action was gripping, the intrigue compelling, and the worldbuilding impressive. Despite that, it still manages to strike that perfect balance of having a world that serves the plot and themes well without taking over the story and leading the narrator into description hell, never to escape. This book is not only my first review on the blog, but also my first recommendation, and I would recommend it to the broadest audience possible.</p>

<p>Thanks for reading! Have a great day, contact me if you have any thoughts on the book or on this article, and I hope you’ll come back to the site in the future!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Arkady Martine’s breakout novel is a modern exploration of the cultural significance of empire. Full of political intrigue, enticing flavor, compelling characters, and well-developed relationships, this book is excellent despite minor issues mostly related to language. Highly recommended.]]></summary></entry></feed>